Guide to the Rush Moody, Jr. Federal Power Commission records, 1971-1985 MS 823
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rush Moody, Jr. Federal Power Commission records
1971-1985
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Moody, Rush, Jr.
MS 823
1 Linear Feet 1 box
The collection consists of materials from and related to the term of Rush Moody, Jr. on the Federal Power Commission from 1971 to 1976.
Biographical / Historical
Rush Moody, Jr. was born July 21, 1930 in Alpine, Texas. He grew up in Houston, graduating from John Reagan High School in 1948. He attended Rice Institute for two years before transferring to the University of Texas to pursue a joint BBA/JD degree. After taking a leave of absence to serve in the U.S. Air Force as an intelligence officer stationed at Warren Robins Airbase, he returned to complete his law studies, graduating in 1956 and being admitted to the Texas Bar that same year. He then returned to Houston to take a position with the Baker, Botts, Andrews, Shepherd law firm. In 1960 he resigned from this firm and moved to Midland, Texas to join Stubbman, McRae, Sealy, Laughlin and Browder, becoming a partner in 1963.
With support from Senator John Tower, Moody was appointed in 1971 by President Richard Nixon to a five-year term on the Federal Power Commission. He served ably for three years but found himself increasingly often voting in dissent regarding the Commission's continued regulation of interstate natural gas prices under the Federal Power Act. In 1975 Moody ultimately resigned, in his resignation letter urging President Gerald Ford to pursue a legislative solution to end the natural gas shortages then troubling the Atlantic Seaboard states. He was then appointed by Texas Governor Dolph Briscoe to serve as special counsel, advising him and Lt. Gov. Bill Hobby on energy policy. At this time Moody also helped Senator Lloyd Bentsen draft what became the Natural Gas Policy Act of 1978.
Moody returned to Washington in 1977, working at a number of Texas-based firms to help them develop their energy practice groups. During this time he helped John G. McMillian organize and finance a consortium to build the first natural gas export pipeline from Prudhoe Bay, Alaska to the lower 48 states. After joining Andrews Kurth he went on to serve as managing partner from 1992 until his retirement in 1996. He and his family moved that year from Chevy Chase to Trappe, Maryland, where he died on November 5, 2015.
Content Description
The collection consists of materials related to the service of Rush Moody, Jr. on the Federal Power Commission, to which he was appointed for a five-year term in 1971. Included is biographical and financial information prepared to support the nomination. Correspondence during the term is included, as are newsclippings about it. There are also a report and speeches related to the work of the Commission from years following Moody's term.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored offsite at the Library Service Center and require 24-hour notice for retrieval. Please contact the Woodson Research Center at 713-348-2586 or woodson@rice.edu for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These materials were donated by a son of Rush Moody, Jr., M. Bradford Moody, on December 12, 2018.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in a single general series.
Index Terms
Subjects
Business; Newspapers--Sections, columns, etc.; Oil and gas; Politics and government
Document Types
reports; letters (correspondence); photographs
Subjects (Persons)
Moody, M. Bradford
Subjects (Corporations)
U.S. Federal Power Commission; Natural Gas Policy Act of 1978
- Series I: Rush Moody records
  - Report by Rush Moody, Jr.: The Natural Gas Industry After Partial Deregulation, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1985 Management Conference of Northern Plains Natural Gas Co. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Speech: Future Market for Industrial Gas Sales, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Speech: Remarks of Rush Moody, Jr. Before Gas Men's Roundtable of Washington, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Speech given in Boston for New England Newswriters Assn., 1977-09-09 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Speech: Natural Gas Issues, 1977 at Nat'l. Conf. of Lieutenant Governors, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - State of Texas Office of State-Federal Relations correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Federal Power Commission correspondence, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Report by Rush Moody, Jr. for Federal Power Commission "1974 – the Gathering Storm" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Federal Power Commission correspondence, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Federal Power Commission correspondence, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Federal Power Commission correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Federal Power Commission correspondence, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Correspondence related to 1971 nomination to Federal Power Comm. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Congressional Record, 1971-07-20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Financial information prepared for 1971 nomination (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Personal Statement, drafts and finished text, prepared for nomination, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Nomination notes and correspondence, 1971, Federal Power Commission (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Business correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Personal correspondence, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Biographical data, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Oil and gas notes, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - News clippings, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rush Moody, Jr. Ephemera, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)